I started with paragliding.
لقد بدأت بالتحليق المظلي
Paragliding is taking off from mountains
التحليق المظلي هو الإقلاع من الجبال
with a paraglider, with the possibility to
بمظله ، وفي إمكانك أن
fly cross-country, distance,
تطير عبر بلداً ، أو مسافة
just with the use of thermals to soar.
فقط بإستخدام بدله للتحليق
Also different aerobatic maneuvers are possible
كذلك حركات بهلوانية ومراوغات ممكنة
with a paraglider.
بإستخدام مظله
From there I started with skydiving.
من هناك بدات القفز المظلي
In this picture you can see
في هذه الصورة ترون
there is a four-way skydive,
هناك أربعه طرق للتحليق
four people flying together,
أربعة أشخاص يطيرون سوياً
and on the left hand side it's the camera flier
وعلى اليسار هناك طائرالتصوير
with the camera mounted to his helmet
بكميرا مركبة على خوذته
so he can film the whole jump,
ليتمكن من تصوير كامل القفزة
for the film itself and also for the judging.
للفلم نفسه ، وللتقييم
From regular, relative skydiving
من القفز المظلي العادي
I went on to freeflying.
إلى الطيران الحر
Freeflying is more the three-dimensional skydiving.
الطيران الحر هو أكثر من الأبعاد الثلاثة للقفز المظلي
You can see the skydiver with the red suit,
يمكنكم أن تروا هذا الغواص الجوي بالبدلة الحمراء
he's in a stand-up position.
وهو في وضع الإستعداد
The one with the yellow-green suit,
والأخر بالبدلة الصفراء والخضراء
he's flying head-down.
هو يطير رأسياً للأسفل
And that's me in the background, carving around the whole formation
وهذا أنا في الخلفية ، لأشكل التشكيلة
in freefall also, with the helmet cam
وفي القفز الحر أيضاً، و بكميرا في الخوذة
to film this jump.
لتصوير هذه القفزة
From freeflying I went on to skysurfing.
من الطيران الحر ذهبت إلى التزلج الهوائي
Skysurfing is skydiving with a board on the feet.
والتزلج الهوائي بإستخدام لوح تزلج في الأقدام
You can imagine with this big surface
يمكنك أن تتخيلون بهذا السطح الكبير
of a skysurfing board,
للوح التزلج الهوائي
there is a lot of force, a lot of power.
هناك الكثير من القدرة والكثير من القوة
Of course I can use this power
طبعاً يمكنني إستخدام هذه القوة
for example for nice spinning -- we call it "helicopter moves."
على سبيل المثال كما نسميه حركات الهليكوبتر
From there I went on to wingsuit flying.
من هناك ذهبت إلى الطيران بالبدلة المجنحة
Wingsuit flying is a suit,
الطيران بالأجنحة هو بدلة
that I can make fly, just only with my body.
تمكنني من الطيران فقط بإستخدام جسدي
If I put some tension on my body, tension on my suit,
إذا وضعت بعض الضغط على جسدي ، أضغط على البدلة
I can make it fly. And as you see
بحيث أجعلها تتطير ، كما ترون
the fall rate is much much slower
مقدار السقوط هو أبطأ كثيراً نسبياً
because of the bigger surface.
بسبب السطح الكبير
With a proper body position I'm able to really move forward
بوضعية جسدية مناسبة ، أتمكن حقيقتاً من التقدم
to gain quite some distance.
لأحصل على المزيد من المسافة
This is a jump I did in Rio de Janeiro.
هذه القفز التي فعلتها في ريو دي جينيرو
You can see the Copacabana on the left-hand side.
تستطيعون أن ترو كوباكابانا على الجانب الأيسر
From there with all the skills and knowledge
من هناك ومع كل المهارات والمعرفه
from paragliding and all the different disciplines
من القفز المظلي إلى مختلف أنواعه
in skydiving, I went on to BASE jumping.
في الغوص الجوي ، إلى القفز القاعدي
BASE jumping is skydiving from fixed objects,
القفز القاعدي هو القفز المظلي من أماكن ثابتة
like buildings, antennae, bridges and earth --
كالمباني ، والواقط الهوائية ، جسور ومن الأرض
meaning mountains, cliffs.
أقصد الجبال ، المنحدرات
It's for sure -- for me -- it's the ultimate feeling
أنها بالتأكيد ، لي ، هي الأحساس الأعظم
of being in free fall,
بكون السقوط الحر
with all the visual references.
مع كل المرئيات ذات العلاقة
So my goal soon was to discover new places
إذا هدفي هو أكتشاف أماكن جديدة
that nobody had jumped before.
لم يقفز منها أحد قبل
So in summer 2000 I was the first to BASE jump
في صيف 2000 ، كنت أول من قفز من قاعدة
the Eiger North Face in Switzerland.
في الجانب المشرق الشمالي من سويسرا
Two years after this, I was the first to BASE jump from Matterhorn,
سنتين بعد ذلك ، كنت من أول قافز قاعدي من على ماتهورن
a very famous mountain that probably
جبل شهير على الأغلب "جبال الألب"ـ
everybody knows in here.
الكل يعرفه هنا
2005 I did a BASE jump from the Eiger, from the Monk and from the Jungfrau,
2005 قد قفزت من على جبل أيقر ، من المونك ، الجونقفراو
three very famous mountains in Switzerland.
ثلاثة جبال شهيرة في سويسرا
The special thing on these three jumps were,
الشي المميز في هذه القفزات الثلاثة كان
I hiked them all and climbed them all in only one day.
انني صعدتها وتسلقتها كلها في يوم واحد
In 2008 I jumped the Eiffel Tower in Paris.
في 2008 ، قفزت من على برج إيفل في باريس
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So with all this knowledge, I also
وبكل هذه المعرفة ، كذلك
wanted to get into stunts.
رغبت في دخول عالم المغامرة
So with some friends we started to do different tricks,
لذا مع بعض الأصدقاء بدأنا ببعض الحركات المتعددة
like for example this jump here,
على سبيل المثال هذه القفزة هنا
I jumped from a paraglider.
لقد قفزت من على مظلة
Or here -- everybody was freezing, pretty much, except me,
وهنا ، الكل كان يتجمد ، كثيرا ، ماعداي
because it was very cold in Austria
لأن الجو كان باردا جدا في النمسا
where we did this filming.
حيث صورنا هذه الفلم
Everybody sitting in a basket,
الكل جالس في السلة
and I was on top of the balloon,
وأنا كنت على أعلى البالون
ready to slide down with my skysurf board.
جاهز لكي أتزلج للأسفل بلوح تزلجي
Or this jump, from a moving truck on the highway.
أو هذه القفزة ، من على شاحنة متحركة على الطريق السريع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Extreme sports on top level like this
الرياضات الخطرة عالية المستوى كهذه
is only possible if you practice step by step,
هي فقط ممكنه إذا تدربت خطوة بخطوة
if you really work hard on your skills
إذا فعلاً عملت بجد على مهاراتك
and on your knowledge.
وعلى معلوماتك
Of course you need to be in physical, very good, condition,
بالطبع تحتاج إلى أن تكون لائقاً جسدياً ، وبوضع جيد جداً
so I'm training a lot.
لذا مازلت أتمرن كثيراً
You need to have the best possible equipment.
أنت تحتاج إلى أفضل المعدات الممكنة
And probably the most important is
وعلى الأغلب الأهم هو
you have to work on your mental skills, mental preparation.
هو أن تعمل على مهراتك العقلية ، وتهيئتك النفسية
And all this to come as close as possible
وكل هذا لنقترب بقدر ما يمكن
to the human dream of being able to fly.
لحلم الإنساني بالقدرة على الطيران
So for 2009,
أذاً لعام 2009
I'm training hard for my two new projects.
أتمرن جيداً على مشروعي الجديدين
The first one, I want to set a world record
المشروع الأول ، أريد أن أسجل رقم عالمي
in flying from a cliff with my wingsuit.
في الطيران من على شفة جبل ببدلتي المجنحة
And I want to set a new record,
وأريد أن أسجل رقم جديداً
with the longest distance ever flown.
لأكبر مسافة تم طيرانها حتى الآن
For my second project,
لمشروعي الثاني ،
I have a sensational idea
لدي فكرة مثيرة
of a jump that never has been done before.
لقفزة لم تحدث من قبل
So now, on the following movie you will see
أذاً الآن في الفلم القادم سترون
that I'm much better in flying a wingsuit
أنني أفضل بالطيران ببدلتي المجنحة
than speaking in English.
من تكلمي بالإنجليزية
Enjoy, and thank you very much.
أستمتعوا ، وشكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
June Cohen: I have some questions.
جون كوهين : لدي بعض الأسئلة
I think we all might have some questions.
أظن أن كلنا لدينا بعض الأسئلة هنا
Question one: so does that actually feel
والسؤال الأول ، هل هذا فعلاً يجعلك تشعر
the way the flying dream does?
كما تشعر بحلم الطيران؟
Because it looks like it might.
لأنها تبدو كذلك
Ueli Gegenschatz: Pretty much. I believe this is probably the closest
أولي جنقنستشاتز : كثيراً ، أعتقد أن هذا هو الأقرب
possibility to come to the dream of being able to fly.
لإمكانية الحصول على حلم القدرة على الطيران
JC: I know the answer to this, but how do you land?
أعرف الجواب على هذا ولكن كيف كنت تهبط ؟
UE: Parachute. We have to open a parachute
المظلة ، علينا أن نفتح المظلة
just seconds before, I would say, impact.
فقط قبل لحظات من ، لأقول ، الإستطدام
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's not possible to land a wingsuit yet.
أنه غير ممكن الهبوط فقط بإستخدام البدلة بعد
JC: Yet. But people are trying. Are you among those --
بعد!! لكن الناس يحاولون ، هل أنت من هؤلاء
you're not going to commit -- are you among those trying to do it?
هل أنت مستعد للإلتزام ، هل أنت من ضمن هؤلاء الذين يودون فعلها
UE: It's a dream. It's a dream. Yeah.
أنه حلم ، أنه حلم ، نعم
We're still working on it and we're
أننا مازلنا نعمل عليها ونحن
developing the wingsuits to get better performance,
نطور بدلة مجنحة للحصول على أفضل أداء
to get more knowledge.
والحصول على معرفة أكثر
And I believe soon.
وأؤمن أنه قريباً
JC: All right. Well we will watch this space. But I have two more questions.
تمام ، إذا سنشاهد هذا الفضاء ولكني لدي سؤالين بعد
What is the -- there was exhaust coming
ما هو - كان هناك دخان قادم
out of the back of the wingsuit. Was that a propelled wingsuit that you were wearing?
من خلف البدلة المجنحة ، هل كانت البدلة التي تلبسها تدفعك للأمام ؟
UE: Nope. It's just smoke.
لا، إنه فقط دخان
JC: Coming off of you?
يخرج منك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
UE: Hopefully not.
أتمنى لا
JC: That seems dangerous.
أنه يبدو خطراً
UE: No, smoke is for two reasons,
لا، الدخان هو لسببين ،
you can see the speed, you can see the way
أنه يمكنك من رؤية السرعه ، حيث ترين الطريق
where I was flying.
حيث كنت أحلق
That's reason number one. And reason number two:
هذا هو السبب الأول ، والسبب الثاني
it's much easier for the camera guy to film
هو أنه أسهل لرجل الكميرا أن يصور
If I'm using smoke.
أذا كنت أستخدم الدخان
JC: Ah, I see. So the wingsuit is set up to deliberately release smoke
أها ، أرى ذلك إذاً البدلة المجنحة هي معده لتخرج دخاناً
so that you can be tracked. One more question.
لكي يمكن متابعتك ، سؤال أخر بعد
What do you do to to cover your face?
ما تفعل لتغطي وجهك ؟
Because I just keep thinking of going that fast
لأنني أفكر بأن الطيران بهذه السرعه
and having your whole face smushed backwards.
وتجد وجهك بكامله مدفوع للخلف
Are you in a helmet? Are you in goggles?
هل كنت تلبس خوذه ؟ أم نظارة مخصصة ؟
UE: The purest and the best feeling would be with only goggles.
الأحساس الأفضل هو بإستخدام فقط النظارات
JC: And is that how you usually fly?
أذا هكذا تطير دائماً ؟
UE: Usually I'm wearing a helmet. In the mountains I'm always wearing a helmet
عادة ما ألبس خوذة ، في الجبال أنا دائماً ألبس خوذه
because of landings -- usually it's difficult --
بسبب الهبوط ، العاده أنه صعب
it's not like regular skydiving where you have like the big landings.
أنه ليس كالقفز المظلي العادي حيث لديك مسافة للهبوط
So you have to be prepared.
لتتمكن من التحضر
JC: Right. Now is there anything you don't do?
أذاً ، هل هناك شي أنت لا تفعله ؟
Do people come to you with projects and say, "We want you to do this!"
هل يأتي الناس لك بمشاريع ويقولون لك "نود أن تعمل ذلك "ـ
and do you ever say, "No, no I'm not going to."
وهل قد قلت مسبقاً " لا لن أفعلها "ـ
UE: Oh of course, of course. Some people have crazy ideas and --
أوه طبعاً ، بالطبع بعض الناس لديهم أفكار مجنونة و ..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
JC: ...a round of applause...
صفقة
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
UE: Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم